Finally, the time has come when you are
finally going on a plane vacation after a long time.
This vacation is very important to get out of the daily stress and take a break.
But if just before the trip, your insurance goes missing
or the flight gets cancelled, suppose
you reach your holiday destination
and your luggage, which contains your
passport and other vital documents, is missing, or you meet with an
accident or
medical issue while traveling, then it is a nightmare.
What will happen in such circumstances,
how will you deal with it? Don't worry, there
is travel insurance, whether you travel to a foreign country or
domestically, that is, within the country.
Travel insurance
offers many benefits. If you are still
confused about travel insurance, then
in this video, we will
know what is travel insurance,
its benefits, how many types of
travel insurance policies are there in India,
what are its benefits and what are not, so state you to
and of the video and know whether you need
travel insurance or not. But
before moving on, subscribe.  Button and
like this video because we post
weekly quality content on personal finance and investing to help you build your health.
[Music]
[Applause]
Before understanding the essentials of travel insurance, let's
understand what travel insurance
is. The name suggests travel insurance today. Travel
insurance is a general insurance policy
that covers different expenses like
medical expenses, flight cancellation, loss of
luggage, legal expenses, and other
losses while traveling domestically or abroad.
It protects you from any unforeseen
damages, medical issues, etc., and their
associated financial costs.
Travel insurance
is beneficial for both domestic and international travel, especially
for those who travel frequently abroad. When you
buy a travel insurance policy, you will
pay the insurance company, and the
insurance company will compensate you for the losses incurred during your travel.
If you are wondering what
travel insurance does apart from medical expenses
like flight cancellation, loss of luggage, and legal
expenses, then do not worry; the
bill will be covering them briefly in this.
Video: Which Date You Want When you
plan a holiday, you should be
prepared for emergencies that
can impact you financially and
turn your holiday into a nightmare.
Travel insurance is like a safety net
that protects you while you're on holiday. Let's move on to the
next part of our video.
What are the benefits of travel insurance?
Imagine you're traveling abroad, you're insured,
and you need to be hospitalized.
Who will bear the cost?
Medical expenses in some foreign countries can be
3 to 5 times higher than in India.
If you don't have travel insurance,
you'll bear all these expenses. But if you have
travel insurance, the
insurance company will cover your hospital expenses, which will keep you financially
safe. One of the biggest advantages of booking your trip with travel insurance is that it helps in case of
health issues or medical
emergencies. Travel
insurance will cover the cost of hospitalization, ambulance
charges, and other related charges.
Did you know that some travel
insurance plans also cover pandemics?
Imagine your flight.
What happens if the flight gets cancelled? Don't worry, if you have travel insurance, the
entire amount for the trip will be safe in case of flight cancellation. You have
reached your destination and your baggage (
wallet or passport) has been lost. What will you do now? Did you know?
Airlines handle approximately 25
million bags every year. A travel
insurance policy will cover the loss of your baggage and will
also provide an amount for buying essential items until your baggage is found.
In some cases, if a third
party suffers accidental damage due to your mistake,
your travel insurance policy will cover that too.
Sir, have you
understood the importance of travel insurance by now? Let me
tell you an interesting fact.
Algeria, Iran,
Israel, Nepal, UAE and some of the countries listed on the screen have made
travel insurance mandatory for international tourists. If
you are planning to travel to any of these 30 countries,
then
definitely take travel insurance. Some of you might be wondering
if you are planning to study abroad, will there be
unexpected events there?  You
can insure yourself against expenses. Yes,
student travel and shore insurance can reduce this. There are
many other types of travel insurance
plans that you should know about.
So let's now know about the various
types of travel insurance policies available in India. Choose according to
your needs. The first type of
travel insurance plan is the domestic
travel insurance plan.
If you are traveling within India, then the
domestic travel insurance plan will cover
you against accidents, medical problems,
flight cancellations,
delayed baggage, situations like the IT sector,
and emergencies. The
next type is the international travel
insurance plan. This type of plan covers
you for traveling abroad.
This plan covers a wider range of travel options like overseas travel, holidays, study
of bread, business meetings, extras, etc. In
this plan,
you get medical and dental expense packages
and passport insurance, which are covered for trip cancellations, flight
delays, etc. The
next type of travel insurance plan is the single
trip travel insurance plan. If you are traveling
only abroad, then
this travel insurance policy is for you.
This plan covers a
specific trip for a specified number of days, clearly mentioned in the policy,
starting from the departure date till the return date.
Like other plans, this plan also covers medical emergencies,
baggage loss, flight cancellation, and other such
events. The next
travel insurance plan is the multi-
trip travel insurance plan. If you
travel more than two to three times a year, then
this policy is for you. Usually,
businessmen and corporate employees
prefer it because it helps save a lot of money.
This insurance
plan covers fast food consumption, accidents,
emergencies, medical evacuation, second hand baggage, consignment
or dairy, and any
other number of things specified by the insurance company. The
next plans are individual and
family travel insurance plans. Are you
going on a solo trip or are you going to
meet your family abroad? If you are
traveling alone, you
can take individual travel insurance plans. This
policy covers accidents, medical and dental expenses, and other
non-medical
factors like baggage loss, passport cancellation. On the other hand, family travel insurance plans cover
Family travel insurance plans are ideal for those planning a holiday with a foreign country.
In this too, the policy holder's small
family covers the cost of baggage, medical
expenses, passport, etc. The
last type of travel
insurance policy is student travel
insurance policy. Do you know that in the last 6 years,
30 lakh Indian students have gone for higher studies.
Students pursuing higher education may face challenges like
medical and financial issues due to expected events.
Student travel insurance
policy comes in handy here. Student travel
insurance plan is for students studying or going for
education.
This policy provides financial and medical support
in case of emergency during the student's stay in a foreign country.
This policy is compassionate enough,
meaning that if you are insured with multiple travel plans, then
a family member can come and meet you and the
travel insurance cost will be borne by you.
Apart from this, it will also protect you from luggage loss, flight
cancellation, personal liability, etc.
We have been continuously advocating that
travelling insurance plans have medical emergency
packages and flights.  It provides protection against cancellation and setbacks.
But do you
want to know about the exact events
that travel insurance covers?
So, here you can make your own decisions. Let's
discuss what travel insurance covers.
Different insurance companies
may cover different risks, but the
most common risks include: Personal
accident, loss and theft of baggage,
cancellation of flight, missing connections, loss
and loss of equipment, such as
laptops, mobile phones,
documents, such as passports, driving
licenses, etc., legal expenses if needed,
cancellation of flight booking, hijacking, personal
liability, trip cancellation, dental
treatment relief, emergency vacation, date
of death, disability of the deceased, in case of
emergency, hotel extension,
hospital stay, daily cash allowance.
Insurance policies cover various risks,
but keep in mind that not all risks are included.
Many travel insurance plans
offer the option to add extra coverage for additional risks at an add-on premium.  It is very important to keep in mind what is included
and what is excluded.
What are the exclusions in travel insurance plan? Just as different
insurance policies have different inclusions,
similarly they also have different exclusions.
But some common exclusions are:
Firstly, travel insurance does not cover the existing
medical issues of the policy holder.
Therefore,
if you have any illness or health issue before traveling, the
insurance company will not cover it.
Secondly, if the policy holder incurs
any medical expenses due to involvement in adventure activities like bunny jumping, rock climbing, guide diving etc. in India, the travel
insurance will not cover it. Additionally, the
insurance company will
not provide any benefit in case of injury or injury caused due to using any illegal drugs or consuming alcohol while driving. For example, if you meet with an accident due to drinking alcohol, the
insurance company will not provide any compensation.
Apart from this, if treatment is done through Ayurveda, Homeopathy and
cosmetic surgery, the
policy does not cover any medical course.
If you  If
someone leaves their passport, luggage, or other items behind,
their life will not be covered.
Hospital
expenses or medical expenses incurred due to self-injury will not be covered by the insurance.
Now that you understand what a travel
insurance policy covers and
what it does not cover, it will be
easier for you to customize a policy based on your needs.
When planning your trip, it's important to
select the right travel insurance plan. Keep in
mind
which countries the travel insurance plan covers, the
duration of your trip, whether you're traveling alone
or in a group, and the
amount of coverage provided.
These factors should be kept in mind when choosing a travel insurance plan based on your needs.
Furthermore, during the
ongoing pandemic, you should
look for a travel insurance plan that
includes the COVID-19 vaccine. You can enjoy
your trip with peace of mind by choosing the right travel insurance plan, knowing
you're prepared for any unexpected events. Have
you ever had a
travel mishap that could have been
avoided with travel insurance?
Share your story in the comments below. Please
note:  The video is for informational purposes only
and is not a substitute for any professional advice.
If you found this video helpful,
hit the subscribe button and don't forget to
share it with your friends and family. Thanks for
watching.